Franz Alexander MD Papers Finding Aid
Oskar Diethelm Library
Franz Alexander MD Papers
1901 - 1986
1930 - 1964
This collection contains the papers of Franz Alexander, a renowned Hungarian psychiatrist and psychoanalyst who is often described as one of the founders of psychosomatic medicine for his work in identifying emotional tension as a cause of physical illness and was also known for using psychoanalytic theories to study criminal behavior. The collection has 6 series: Franz Alexander Correspondence (1927-1986), Franz Alexander General Files (1931-1981), Franz Alexander Miscellaneous and Personal Files (1901-1956), Anita Alexander Files (1932-1964), Reprints and Publications (1925-1961), and Photographs (1927-1964).
7.67 linear feet (17 boxes)
Alexander, Franz, 1891-1964
Oskar Diethelm Library DeWitt Wallace Institute of Psychiatry: History, Policy and the Arts Weill Cornell Medical College 525 East 68th Street, Box 140 New York, NY 10065
2014.0001
The Franz Alexander Papers were donated by the Pollock family in 2014. These papers were given to Dr. George Pollock by Franz Alexander’s children in 1992. George Pollock, a psychiatrist, was a former director of the Institute for Psychoanalysis in Chicago and former president of the American Psychiatric Association. He had a close personal and professional relationship with Alexander and was working on a biography of him at the time of his death in 2003.
Folder 27 in Box 3 of Series I: Franz Alexander Correspondence, is restricted due PHI (private health information). It has been removed from Box 3 and stored separately.
Franz Gabriel Alexander (1891-1964) was a renowned Hungarian psychiatrist and psychoanalyst who is often described as one of the founders of psychosomatic medicine for his work in identifying emotional tension as a cause of physical illness and was also known for using psychoanalytic theories to study criminal behavior. Alexander was born on January 22, 1891 in Budapest and enrolled as the first student in the Berlin Psychoanalytic Institute in 1919. While there, he underwent a personal analysis with Hanns Sachs and later became an assistant at the Institute. His first book, The Psychoanalysis of the Total Personality (1930), grew out of a lecture series he presented at the Institute in 1924 and 1925. Alexander was invited to the United States in 1930 to serve as Visiting Professor of Psychoanalysis at the University of Chicago, a new post created specifically for him. After a year in Chicago, Alexander moved to Boston and completed a study of delinquency with William Healy. This work was presented in their book, Roots of Crime (1935).
In 1932, he returned to Chicago to help establish the Chicago Institute for Psychoanalysis and served as its director until 1956. As director, he sought to attract many analysts and students who researched and studied emotional disorders and psychosomatic diseases. He published another book in 1950, Psychosomatic Medicine: Its Principles and Practices. Alexander also served as a faculty member in the Department of Psychiatry at the University of Illinois Medical School in Chicago from 1938 to 1956. He held many other posts, fellowships, and consultancies during his professional years. In 1956, he became Chief of Staff of the new Psychiatric Department at Mount Sinai Hospital in Los Angeles and Professor of Psychiatry at the University of Southern California. He also served as a training and supervising analyst at the Southern California Psychoanalytic Institute. He died March 8, 1964 in Palm Springs, California.
Alexander, Franz, 1891-1964; Psychosomatic medicine; Psychoanalysis; Pollock, George H.; Institute for Psychoanalysis; Criminal behavior; Alexander, Anita, 1895-1984; Van Buren, Abigail, 1918-2013; Dear Abby (Newspaper column); American Psychiatric Association
This collection contains correspondence, documents, publications and professional writings, notes, photographs, and other personal and professional materials dating from 1901 to 1986, with the bulk of the material dating to the 1930s. The majority of the materials are in English, but there are a few letters and documents in German, Hungarian, and Italian. The papers are divided into six series: Franz Alexander Correspondence (1927-1986), Franz Alexander General Files (1931-1981), Franz Alexander Miscellaneous and Personal Files (1901-1956), Anita Alexander Files (1932-1964), Reprints and Publications (1925-1961), and Photographs (1927-1964). The papers came to the library already organized into categories by correspondence, other files, reprints and publications, and photographs. This original order has been maintained. In most cases, the individual folder structure has also been maintained, as the correspondence and the reprints and publications were organized alphabetically. An index was completed at an unknown date listing the contents of each of the original boxes and the title of each folder, and a copy of this list is stored with the collection.
Franz Alexander Correspondence: This series, arranged alphabetically by author, contains Alexander’s correspondence with colleagues and other entities, mostly professional in nature, but some personal. It includes correspondence related to appointments, translations, writings, talks, requests for articles, and requests for immigration assistance. Miscellaneous materials are filed at the end of the series.
Franz Alexander General Files: This series is arranged alphabetically by the name of the organization, company, or group and has been kept in the original order. It includes correspondence, papers, meeting programs, and requests for lectures. Miscellaneous materials are filed at the end of the series.
Franz Alexander Miscellaneous and Personal Files: This series includes lectures, articles, immigration and insurance documents, school transcripts for Alexander, and newspaper clippings, among other materials.
Anita Alexander Files: This series contains papers of Anita Alexander, Franz’s wife. It includes financial documents, receipts, condolences on Alexander’s death, correspondence with friend Pauline Phillips (Dear Abby), other correspondence, and materials related to Anita’s paintings in galleries and exhibits.
Reprints and Publications: This series is arranged alphabetically by title and predominantly contains reprints of Alexander’s published writings. The reprints arrived arranged alphabetically with a list of titles for each folder, but the folders have been reorganized. The original lists are stored with this series.
Photographs: This series contains professional portraits of Franz Alexander, some professional portraits of Anita and daughters Kiki and Silvia Alexander, many family snapshots and vacation photographs, and a photograph of Franz’s father, Bernard Alexander.
- Franz Alexander Correspondence
  - Ackerman, Dr. Nathan W., on cancelled speech, Topeka, Kansas, 1936 (Box 1)
  - Adamic, Louis on Hungarians in America for Adamic’s book, A Nation of Nations, 1938 - 1939 (Box 1)
  - Adler, Mortimer J. on Adler lectures, introduction to Adler’s book, Daily Maroon, 1936 - 1937; 1940 (Box 1)
  - Alexander, Paul, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Alinksky, Saul D., 1938 (Box 1)
  - Bartemeier, Dr. Leo H., 1935 - 1938 (Box 1)
  - Bergler, Edmund (in German), 1935 (Box 1)
  - Berczeller, Dr. L., c. 1927 (Box 1)
  - Berkeley-Hill, Dr. Owen, 1935 (Box 1)
  - Bernfeld, Dr. Siegfried on asthma research, San Francisco study group, 1937 - 1938; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Beyer, Rudolf, 1933 (Box 1)
  - Bibring, Dr. Edward on Dr. Piska, Ernest Jones Birthday, 1938 - 1939 (Box 1)
  - Biddle, Dr. Sydney G., 1938 (Box 1)
  - Bodman, Harold, 1934 (Box 1)
  - Boehm, Felix, 1933 - 1935 (Box 1)
  - Boisen, Anton T. on case seminar, 1936 - 1937 (Box 1)
  - Bonaparte, Marie, 1934; 1938 (Box 1)
  - Borg, Mrs. Sidney C., 1938 (Box 1)
  - Bornstein-Windholz, Mrs. Steff, 1938 (Box 1)
  - Bowman, Dr. Karl M., 1938 - 1939 (Box 1)
  - Brioni Hotel, 1936 (Box 1)
  - Bychowski, Dr. Gustaw, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Carlson, Robert, 1937 (Box 1)
  - Carson, Joseph Jr., 1939 (Box 1)
  - Chalat, Dr. J.H., 1939 (Box 1)
  - Chapman, Dr. Ross McC., 1938 (Box 1)
  - Cohn, Franz, 1935 - 1936 (Box 1)
  - Dallenbach, Dr. Karl M., 1937 (Box 1)
  - D’Amore, Dr. Arcangelo on copies for Dr. George Pollock, historical papers on the founding of the Chicago Institute for Psychoanalysis, 1932 - 1934; 1965; 1973 (Box 2)
  - De la Croix, Gertrude, 1935 - 1938 (Box 2)
  - Dickinson, Lora T., 1940 (Box 2)
  - Dukes, Dr. Geza, 1938 (Box 2)
  - Dunbar, Dr. H. Flanders, 1938 - 1939 (Box 2)
  - Elgart, Saul, 1938 - 1939 (Box 2)
  - Eliasberg, Dr. Wladimir, 1939 (Box 2)
  - Emery, Dr. E. Van Norman and Emery, Dr. Felice M., 1936 - 1939 (Box 2)
  - English, Dr. O. Spurgeon, 1938 (Box 2)
  - Ernestine, Mlle. Mathilde, 1937 (Box 2)
  - Ets-Hokin, Louis, 1939 (Box 2)
  - Falstein, Eugene I. on patient cases, 1937 (Box 2)
  - Feigenbaum, Dr. Dorian, 1936 (Box 2)
  - Feigl, Maria, 1937 (Box 2)
  - Finkelstein, Lizzie L. (in German), Undated (Box 2)
  - Flournoy, Dr. Henry, 1937 (Box 2)
  - Folsom, Professor Joseph K., 1937 (Box 2)
  - Forel, O. L., 1936 (Box 2)
  - Forsyth, Dr. David, 1935 - 1938 (Box 2)
  - Frank, Dr. Erich (in German), 1939 (Box 2)
  - Frankenthal, Dr. Ludwig, 1939 (Box 2)
  - Freud, Dr. Martin (some in German) on translation of Alexander’s book The Medical Value of Psychoanalysis, into German, personal business, 1932 - 1937 (Box 2)
  - Friedemann, Dr. Max (some in German), 1936 (Box 2)
  - Friedlander, Dr. Walter (some in German), 1937 (Box 2)
  - Friedmann, E. (in Hungarian), 1938 (Box 2)
  - Friedmann, Ella, 1938 (Box 2)
  - Friedrich, Dr. Ladislov, 1939 (Box 2)
  - Fromm, Dr. Erich, 1937 (Box 2)
  - Gaus, Professor John M., 1937 - 1939 (Box 2)
  - Gelb, Aldemar (some in German), 1934 (Box 2)
  - Georgie, Leyla, 1937 - 1939 (Box 2)
  - Gerard, Dr. Margaret, 1940 (Box 2)
  - Gerard, Dr. Ralph W., 1939 (Box 2)
  - Germain, Mr. Walter M., Supervisor, Crime Prevention Division, Police Dept., Saginaw, Michigan on delinquent children, 1938 (Box 2)
  - Gero, Dr. Georg (some in German), 1938 (Box 3)
  - Gerst and Sohn, N., firm, 1937 (Box 3)
  - Gluck, Dr. Edith, Undated (Box 3)
  - Gordon, Dr. William T., 1939 (Box 3)
  - Graber, G.H. (in German), 1935 - 1936; 1938 (Box 3)
  - Greene, J.E., 1937 (Box 3)
  - Groenvald, Dr. A., 1936 - 1937 (Box 3)
  - Gross, Dr. Alfred, Undated (Box 3)
  - Grotjahn, Dr. Martin (some in German), 1936 - 1937 (Box 3)
  - Halberstadt, Max (in German), 1934 (Box 3)
  - Halperin, Lou on Halperin’s notes, 1940; 1951 - 1958 (Box 3)
  - Hamburger, Dr. Walter, mostly personal correspondence, 1938 - 1940 (Box 3)
  - Hartmann, Heinz (some in German), 1933 - 1940 (Box 3)
  - Hayes, Virginia C., 1937 - 1940 (Box 3)
  - Helfmann, Karoly, 1938 - 1939 (Box 3)
  - Henry, Dr. George W., 1937 (Box 3)
  - Herold, Dr. Carl M., 1936 (Box 3)
  - Hertz, Leona Jane, 1939 - 1940 (Box 3)
  - Hill, Dr. Lewis B., 1937 - 1939 (Box 3)
  - Hoffer, Dr. Wilhelm, 1933; 1937 (Box 3)
  - Hoffman, Dr. Harry R., 1936 (Box 3)
  - Holtz, Dr. Edward, 1937 (Box 3)
  - Hosmer, Dr. C.M., 1936 - 1937 (Box 3)
  - Hull, Dr. Clark L. on notice of informal seminar, 1936 (Box 3)
  - Hunt, Professor William A., 1936 (Box 3)
  - Inbau, Fred E., 1938 (Box 3)
  - RESTRICTED Inch, Dr. George F., 1938 (Box 3)
  - Insinger, Fred on renting the Alexanders’ house in La Jolla, CA, 1937 (Box 3)
  - Kardiner, Dr. A., 1937 (Box 3)
  - Karinthy, Mrs. F. (some in Hungarian), 1939 (Box 3)
  - Kasanin, Dr. Jacob, 1936 - 1938 (Box 3)
  - Kaufman, Dr. M. Ralph, 1938 - 1939 (Box 3)
  - Kaysen, Dr. Ralph, 1937; 1939 (Box 3)
  - Korosy, K. de, 1939 (Box 3)
  - Lamlp, Hans (some in German), 1938 (Box 3)
  - Landauer, Karl (some in German), 1933 - 1935; 1939 (Box 3)
  - Lange, Paul, some in German, 1933 (Box 3)
  - Lape, Esther Everett on history and programming of the Chicago Institute for Psychoanalysis, 1938 (Box 3)
  - Le Bourgeois, Mrs. J.C., 1939 (Box 3)
  - Lenz, Dr. Otto on vacation at Hotel Brioni, Italy, 1934 - 1935 (Box 3)
  - Levine, Dr. Maurice, 1939 (Box 3)
  - Levy, Dr. David M., 1936 - 1938 (Box 4)
  - Lewis, Dr. Nolan D.C., 1937 - 1938 (Box 4)
  - Lewy, Dr. Ernst (in German), 1936 (Box 4)
  - Libbey, Betsy, 1934 (Box 4)
  - Lindenau, Kaete (in German), 1933 (Box 4)
  - Lippman, Dr. Hyman S., 1937 (Box 4)
  - Lippmann, Dr. Werner, 1939 (Box 4)
  - Loeb, Lotta, 1934 (Box 4)
  - Loeb, Virginia, 1937 (Box 4)
  - Maiti, Dr. H.P., 1937 (Box 4)
  - Major, Elizabeth (some in Hungarian), 1933 - 1938 (Box 4)
  - Malamud, Dr. William, 1938 (Box 4)
  - McMurry, Dr. Robert N., 1937 - 1938 (Box 4)
  - Medgyesy, Lazslo (some in Hungarian) on suicide prevention in Budapest, 1936 - 1937 (Box 4)
  - Merloni, Raffaele (in Italian), 1933 (Box 4)
  - Mihalyne, Neimeth (in Hungarian), 1935 (Box 4)
  - Mohr, Dr. George to Dr. Edward Bibring (some in German), 1932 - 1937; 1976 (Box 4)
  - de Monchy, Dr. S.J.R., 1935 (Box 4)
  - Muller-Braunschweig, Dr. Carl (some in German) on Deutsche Psychoanalytische Gesellschaft, 1933 - 1937 (Box 4)
  - Nacht, Dr. S. (some in French), 1938 - 1939 (Box 4)
  - Naef, Dr. Elisabeth (in German), 1933 (Box 4)
  - Odier, C.T. (in German), 1934 (Box 4)
  - van Ophuijsen, Dr. J.H.W., 1935 (Box 4)
  - Oppenheimer, Dr. Erik, 1937 (Box 4)
  - Ostermann on article for Mothers’ Aid Message magazine, Undated (Box 4)
  - Papi, Gennaro, 1936 (Box 4)
  - Parmenter, Dr. Richard, 1939 (Box 4)
  - Peck, Dr. Martin W., 1937 (Box 4)
  - Pelenyi, His Excellency John, 1937 (Box 4)
  - Perenyi, Baron Zsigmund, 1937 (Box 4)
  - Pick, Dr. E. P. (some in German), 1938 (Box 4)
  - Piper, William (in German), 1935 (Box 4)
  - Porter, Cynthia, 1939 (Box 4)
  - Rado, Dr. Sandor, 1934 - 1938 (Box 4)
  - Roellenbleck, Dr. E. (in German), 1933 (Box 4)
  - Ronjat, Louis (in French), Undated (Box 4)
  - Samu, Dr. Szemere (some in Hungarian), 1936 - 1937 (Box 4)
  - Sarasin, Dr. Philipp (in German), 1934; 1936 (Box 4)
  - Schuster, Dr. Julius (in German and Hungarian), 1933 (Box 4)
  - Segal, Arthur (some in German) on painting (art), 1936 - 1939 (Box 4)
  - Sicu, Ernst (in German), 1934 (Box 4)
  - Silberstein, Mrs. Bernard (some in German), 1938 (Box 4)
  - Silverberg, Dr. Mabel G., 1937 (Box 4)
  - Simmel, Dr. Ernest-Jones in Vienna, 1936 - 1938 (Box 4)
  - Singer, Dr. H. Douglas, 1937 - 1940 (Box 4)
  - Skekely, Mr. Bela (some in Hungarian), 1935 - 1936 (Box 4)
  - Sloane, Dr. Paul, 1937 (Box 4)
  - Smeliansky, Dr. Chana (in German), 1934 (Box 5)
  - Solomon, Dr. Alfred P., 1938 (Box 5)
  - Somers, Dr. Melvin R., 1939 (Box 5)
  - Stern, Alfred K. on memorial meeting, 1936; 1986 (Box 5)
  - Storfer, A. J. (in German), 1938 (Box 5)
  - Sziklay, Andor, editor of Szabadsag, a Hungarian publication, 1936 (Box 5)
  - Szabo, Dr. Istvan (some in Hungarian), 1938 (Box 5)
  - Tage-Buch, a German publication, 1933 (Box 5)
  - Taylor, Katharine W., 1938 - 1939 (Box 5)
  - Tenney, Edith on piano lessons for his daughters, 1936 (Box 5)
  - Thompson, Dr. Joseph C., 1937 (Box 5)
  - Tumpeer, Dr. I. Harrison, 1938 - 1939 (Box 5)
  - Urbantschitsch, Dr. Rudolph (in German), 1938 (Box 5)
  - van Emden, Dr. J.E.G. (in German), 1935 (Box 5)
  - Walkowitz, Mr. Abraham, Undated (Box 5)
  - Walling, Mrs. Willoughby George, 1938 (Box 5)
  - Washburne, Dr. Annette C., 1939 (Box 5)
  - Watson, Dr. James on case histories, 1936 (Box 5)
  - Wechsler, Dr. I.S., 1938 (Box 5)
  - Weil, Victor H., 1939 - 1940 (Box 5)
  - Weiss, Edoardo, 1938 - 1939 (Box 5)
  - Zilboorg, Dr. Gregory on Lectures on Sex Crimes, IV - Sex Murders, Undated (Box 5)
  - Zinn, Earl, 1935 - 1938; 1940 (Box 5)
  - Zulliger, Dr. Hans, in German on publication of translation of “From the Unconscious Life of Our School Children” by Zullinger, 1937 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence (some in Hungarian and German), 1932; 1935 - 1939; 1983 (Box 5)
- Franz Alexander General Files
  - Abraham Lincoln Centre, Chicago, 1942 - 1943 (Box 6)
  - Alfred Dunhill of London, Inc. on cigars, 1937 (Box 6)
  - American Association of Psychiatric Social Workers, Indianapolis, IN, 1937 (Box 6)
  - American Board of Psychiatry and Neurology, 1937 - 1938 (Box 6)
  - American Journal of Sociology material regarding article titled “The Contribution of Psychoanalysis to Sociology”, 1936 - 1937 (Box 6)
  - American Medical Association, 1936 - 1938 (Box 6)
  - American Mercury publication, 1942 - 1943 (Box 6)
  - American Orthopsychiatric Association correspondence and draft papers, “Culture and Personality,” section meeting, 1936 - 1938 (Box 6)
  - American Psychiatric Association annual meeting in Pittsburg, PA, Alexander’s paper “Remarks About the Inferiority Feelings to Guilt Feelings”, 1937 (Box 6)
  - American Psychiatric Association annual meeting San Francisco, CA, 1938 (Box 6)
  - American Psychiatric Association annual meeting, Chicago, 1939 (Box 6)
  - American Psychiatric Association miscellaneous correspondence, 1937 - 1938 (Box 6)
  - American Psychoanalytic Association Emergency Committee on Relief and Immigration and placement queries, 1933 - 1934; 1938; 1943 (Box 6)
  - American Psychoanalytic Association meetings in Chicago and San Francisco, Alexander’s paper “Psychoanalysis Comes of Age,” resolutions to be submitted, 1938 (Box 6)
  - American Psychoanalytic Association meeting, 1939 (Box 6)
  - American Psychoanalytic Association miscellaneous correspondence, 1936 - 1938 (Box 6)
  - American Psychoanalytic Association, Dr. Lawrence Kubie correspondence, 1937 - 1938; 3 folders (Box 6, Box 7)
  - American Psychoanalytic Association, Ernest Simmel correspondence (some in German), 1934 - 1938 (Box 7)
  - Atlanta Graduate Medical Assembly, 1939 (Box 7)
  - Atlanta Psychoanalytic Society, 1935 (Box 7)
  - Audio-Scriptions, Inc., NY on recording of speech by Alexander, 1937 (Box 7)
  - Bauhaus, the New American School of Design on 2 lectures by Dr. Alexander, correspondence, 1938 (Box 7)
  - Center for Advanced Study in the Behavioral Sciences, 1957 (Box 7)
  - Central Neuropsychiatric Association, 1939 (Box 7)
  - Chatham Hotel, New York, 1938 - 1939 (Box 7)
  - Chicago Academy of Criminology, 1936 - 1939 (Box 7)
  - Chicago City Junior Colleges, 1936 (Box 7)
  - Child Research Clinic of the Woods Schools, Langhorne PA, 1937 - 1938 (Box 7)
  - Debrecen University Budapest, 1938 (Box 7)
  - Encyclopaedia Sexualis on Alexander’s entry “Psychoanalysis, Definitions and Terms in”, 1935 (Box 7)
  - Europa Theatre, in Hungarian, 1937 (Box 7)
  - “Flexibility in Psychotherapy” Institute for Psychoanalysis on rough manuscript of paper by Alexander, French, et al (Eds.), later published as “Psychoanalytic Therapy: Principles and Application” by Ronald Press, 1946, 1945 (Box 7)
  - Harris Clinic, Fort Worth TX on searching for a psychiatrist with psychoanalytic training to join the clinic, 1939 (Box 7)
  - House of Representatives on Joint Resolution 79 providing for the establishment of department to be known as “Department of Science, Art and Literature” later as the “Bureau of Fine Arts”, includes copy of the resolution, 1937 (Box 7)
  - Hungarian Club of Chicago invites, programs, clippings, membership info, copies of a talk given by Alexander at the Club on May 28, 1936 about Louis Kossuth, copies (in English and Italian), 1936 - 1937 (Box 7)
  - Illinois State Medical Society Annual Meeting, 1938 - 1939 (Box 7)
  - Indiana Society for Mental Hygiene, 1940 (Box 7)
  - Institute for Psychoanalysis, Chicago on Education Committee meetings, 1936 - 1938 (Box 7)
  - Institute for Psychoanalysis, Chicago on Five Year report, 1937 - 1938 (Box 7)
  - Institute for Psychoanalysis, Chicago on fundraising, solicitations, advisory boards, 1936 - 1940 (Box 7)
  - Institute for Psychoanalysis, Chicago on inventory of Institute, Undated (Box 7)
  - Institute for Psychoanalysis, Chicago on lectures and seminars, 1940 (Box 7)
  - Institute for Psychoanalysis, Chicago on physicians’ course, 1939 - 1940 (Box 7)
  - Institute for Psychoanalysis, Chicago on social workers-materials for course, 1937 - 1938 (Box 7)
  - Institute for Psychoanalysis, Chicago on Trustees meetings, 1936 - 1937 (Box 8)
  - Institute for Psychoanalysis, Chicago on Trustees meeting, 1938 (Box 8)
  - Institute for Psychoanalysis, London on Report for the Year Ending June 30th, 1935 (Box 8)
  - International Criminology Society, 1937 (Box 8)
  - Loomis Sanatorium, 1937 (Box 8)
  - Mental Hygiene Society of Maryland, 1937 (Box 8)
  - Minnesota State Conference of Social Work, 1937 (Box 8)
  - Pennsylvania School of Social Work, 1937 (Box 8)
  - Psychological Exposition, 1938 (Box 8)
  - Society for Research in Child Development, 1935 - 1938 (Box 8)
  - Sociometry, A Journal of Inter-Personal Relations, 1937 (Box 8)
  - Southern Psychiatric Association, 1938 (Box 8)
  - St. Louis Provident Association, 1937 (Box 8)
  - Swarthmore College on his daughter’s application, 1937 (Box 8)
  - University of Chicago, 1931 (Box 8)
  - William Alanson White correspondence from 1932-35 with copies of the personal correspondence of William Alanson White from the National Archives requested in 1981 by Jerome Kavka of the Institute for Psychoanalysis, Chicago and given to George Pollock in 1981, 1932 - 1981 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, professional and other organizations, 1933 - 1938 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, publishers, 1933 - 1937; 1942 - 1943 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, reprint acknowledgements, 1936 - 1937 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, requests for therapy, positions, referrals, recommendations, 1938 - 1942 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous files, including speeches, papers, Freud’s 80th birthday, and contains paper written by Alexander, “Commemoration of Sigmund Freud on His Eightieth Birthday” and “Fundamental Concepts of Psychosomatic Research: Psychogenesis-Conversion-Specificity”, 1936 - 1942 (Box 8)
- Franz Alexander Miscellaneous and Personal Files
  - Psychoanalysis in Medicine, 10 lectures by Dr. Alexander including contract with publisher W.W. Norton, 1932 - 1933 (Box 9)
  - Chicago Magazine, Oct 1956 issue featuring Alexander on cover with article “Franz Alexander: the Man Who Brought Freud Here” an interview with his daughter Francesca Alexander (Box 9)
  - Drawing by patient, signed Nogo, Undated (Box 9)
  - Cartoons, to Dr. Hitzig, signed by “Major” [a patient?], Undated (Box 9)
  - Immigration documents and correspondence, Franz and Anita Alexander, 1931 - 1934; 1941 (Box 9)
  - Franz Alexander’s personal mailing list and address cards, Undated (Box 9)
  - Insurance documents, 1932 - 1938 (Box 9)
  - Insurance documents (most in German), 1933 - 1934 (Box 9)
  - San Diego Consolidated Gas and Electric Company, 1936 - 1937 (Box 9)
  - The Army and Navy Club of Chicago, 1935 - 1938 (Box 9)
  - School transcripts for Alexander from a school in Hungary, Gimnaziumi Bizonyitvany (in Hungarian), 1901 - 1908 (Box 9)
  - Biography of Alexander written after his death, unknown author, c. 1964 (Box 9)
  - H.H. Bradley Fountain Lunch, 1936 - 1937 (Box 9)
  - Paper titled “Mathias Zdarsky – Pioneer of Alpine Skiing” by Dr. Irma Hift-Schnier and Ester J. Mohr, with photographs of Zdarsky and a letter from Mohr to David B. Hampton asking if he can find a place to publish the article, 1936 (Box 9)
  - Letters to Franz Alexander, some critical on comment he made in the newspaper about women “bobby soxers” being “part of a trend toward a society dominated by women”, 1946 (Box 9)
  - Items sent to newspapers for publication including “A Joint Statement Prepared by Dr. Franz Alexander and Dr. Thomas M. French” in response to an article about psychoanalysis, 1937 (Box 9)
  - Newspaper clippings, Alexander’s writings The Roots of Crime and The Medical Value of Psychoanalysis clipped into notebooks, 1932 - 1935 (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous newspaper clippings, Undated (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous unidentified items, Undated (Box 9)